William Gropper
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
William Gropper papers
1916-1983
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Gropper, William
3.3 linear feet
The papers of painter, illustrator, muralist, and political activist William Gropper measure 3.3 linear feet and date from 1916-1983. Almost one-half of the collection consists of printed materials, including full issues of New Masses, Liberator, and Der Hammer, all featuring illustrations by Gropper. Circa 600 letters include those written to Gropper by Frank Crowninshield, Robert Henri, Louis Lozowick, Raphael Soyer, and others. Also found are photographs of Gropper, his family, colleagues, and friends, as well as scattered writings and notes, business records, biographical information, three drawings, and a fabric sample designed by Gropper.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Sophie Gropper, Gropper's widow, in 1984.
Related Material
Among the holdings of the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview of William Gropper conducted by Bruce Hooton in 1965. The Louis Lozowick papers contain documentation of Lozowick's research and writings for a biography of Gropper.
The Special Collections Research Center at the Syracuse University Library also holds a collection of William Gropper's papers.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection was digitized in 2007 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.
Biographical Note
William Gropper was born on December 3rd, 1897 in the Lower East Side of Manhattan. His family was impoverished and his parents worked in the New York garment factories. To help his family, Gropper took odd jobs throughout New York City. When he was not busy working, Gropper nurtured his artistic talents by drawing cartoons on sidewalks and the sides of buildings.
In 1912, Gropper began formal art education at the Ferrer School in Greenwich Village where he was influenced by the Ashcan School of social realists, particularly artists Robert Henri and George Bellows. After the Ferrer School, Gropper studied at the New York School of Fine and Applied Arts on a scholarship granted by Frank Alvah Parsons. Following his education, Gropper worked simultaneously at the New York Tribune and Rebel Worker as a draftsman and cartoonist respectively. He continued a career as a cartoonist and illustrator for publications such as Vanity Fair, New Masses, The Nation, Freiheit, and various Jewish and Hebrew publications for more than thirty years. Gropper's cartoons typically portrayed the everyday worker and the injustices he suffered.
Gropper, who was also a painter, produced powerful imagery of social protest. His subjects included industrial strikes and the labor wars of the coal mining and steel industries. Additionally, William Gropper received several commissions from the Federal Arts Project, Works Progress Administration to create murals for various public buildings around the country, including one for the United States Department of the Interior building in Washington, D.C. Here, he created Construction of the Dam to represent the combination of labor and technology to construct various dams on the Colorado River. The Guggenheim Foundation awarded a fellowship to Gropper to travel to the impoverished Dust Bowl region. This trip inspired a series of illustrations that appeared in The Nation. Gropper's trips to Russia and Poland also served to inspire his art.
Later in his career, William Gropper exhibited his artwork throughout the United States and the world. Gropper was also one of the originial members of the Artists Equity Association founded in 1947. Gropper's artwork can be found in the permanent collections of the Smithsonian Institution, The National Gallery of Art, The Butler Institute of American Art, Princeton University, The Phillips Collection, The William J. Clinton Presidential Library as well as many other museums and universities. William Gropper remained in New York City and the surrounding area with his wife, Sophie until his death in 1977.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, illustrator, muralist, and political activist William Gropper measure 3.3 linear feet and date from 1916-1983.
Three folders of scattered Biographical Information are found for William Gropper, his wife Sophie and their children. Business Records consist of lists of artwork, price lists, contracts, receipts, and other financial records. Scattered Writings and Notes include mostly writings about Gropper by others, lists of works of art, and miscellaneous writings. Works of Art include three original drawings by Gropper and a sample of fabric designed by Gropper. Circa 600 letters within the papers were written to William Gropper between 1916 and 1977 (bulk, 1970s), although Sophie Gropper's correspondence is also included. Found here are letters from Frank Crowninshield, Robert Henri, Louis Lozowick, Frank Alva Parsons, Raphael Soyer, and others. There are also letters concerning Gropper's participation in the Federal Art Project and from Ben Horowitz of the Heritage Gallery who represented Gropper's artwork.
Almost one-half of the collection consists of Printed Materials, including full issues of New Masses, Liberator, and Der Hammer, all featuring illustrations by Gropper. Also found are auction and exhibition catalogs, clippings, press releases, and printed reproductions of Gropper's artwork.
Photographs are of Gropper, his family, colleagues, friends, family vacations, and works of art.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Federal Art Project
Subjects-Topical:
Art -- Political aspects; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Political activists
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Drawings
Names:
Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987; Crowninshield, Frank, 1872-1947; Henri, Robert, 1865-1929; Lozowick, Louis, 1892-1973; Gropper, Sophie; Parsons, Frank Alvah, 1868-1930; Horowitz, Benjamin, 1912-; Heritage Gallery
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, circa 1942-1982 (Box 1; 3 Folders)
Series 2: Business Records, circa 1936-1983 (Box 1; 8 Folders)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1947-1978 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Works of Art, circa 1940s, 1952, after 1958 (Box 1, OV 4; 2 Folders)
Series 5: Correspondence, circa 1916-1983 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, circa 1919-1983 (Box 1-3, OV 4; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, after 1937-circa 1980s (Box 3; 0.8 linear feet)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, circa 1942-1982, Series 1:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  This series consists of scattered biographical information, including fingerprint records, resumes, an estate appraisal, Gropper's funeral arrangement information, and immunization records. Information pertaining to Sophie Gropper includes a photograph, diet information and permit. Also included is information concerning the Gropper Family such as estate information, bank records, receipts, and report cards.
  This series is arranged by family name to which the biographical information pertains.
  - William Gropper, 1942-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sophie Gropper, 1972, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gropper Family, 1973, 1974, 1982, (partially scanned) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Business Records, circa 1936-1983, Series 2:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  William Gropper's scattered Business Records include lists of works of art, purchase orders for artwork, bills, royalty information, contracts with museums and publishing companies, bank records and receipts.
  - Price Lists, 1968-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Art Purchase Orders, 1967-1980, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Bills, 1970-1979, (not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Book Royalties, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Contracts, 1936, 1939, 1955, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial and Bank Records, 1974-1977, undated, (not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Receipts, 1963-1969, 1980-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1947-1978, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  This series includes descriptions of Gropper's works of art, lists of works of art, writings by and about Gropper, including a dissertation about the artist by Joseph Anthony Gahn. There is also one folder of scattered minutes of the Committee on Progess of the American Academy of Arts and Letters. It is unclear what role Gropper played on the Committee.
  - Descriptions of Works of Art, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dissertation on Gropper, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lists of Works of Art, 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, Committee on Progress, American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writings about Gropper, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Writings by Gropper, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1953,1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Works of Art, circa 1949, 1952, after 1958, Series 4:; (Box 1, OV 4; 2 folders)
  This series includes three original pen and pencil drawings by William Gropper. One drawing is of three unidentified men which Gropper signs with hebrew characters. A second drawing is a profile of a seated, unidentified man. The last sketch is of an unidentified group of people. A Gropper designed fabric sample is included as well.
  - Drawings, circa 1949, after 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Fabric Sample, 1952, (See Box 4) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Oversized Fabric Sample, 1952 (Box 4 (sol), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, circa 1916-1983, Series 5:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  This series includes letters written to William Gropper from 1916 until 1977, including some photocopies. Very few of William Gropper's responses are in this collection, which are mostly undated. There is also correspondence written by and to Sophie Gropper from 1980 to 1983. Notable correspondents include Louis Lozowick, Frank Crowninshield, Raphael Soyer, Robert Henri, and Frank Alvah Parsons. There are many letters from Ben Horowitz with the Heritage Gallery, which sold Gropper's art. Additionally, there are letters concerning William Gropper's participation in the Works Progress Administration. Correspondence from 1935 documents Gropper's contributions to Vanity Fair magazine before it ceased publication in 1936. Correspondence after Gropper's death is between his widow, Sophie Gropper and various museums, galleries, and publishers.
  Correspondence is arranged chronogically. An Index of Selected Correspondents, provides a more comprehensive list of the letters.
  - Correspondence, 1916-1923 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Printed Material, circa 1919-1983, Series 6:; (Box 1-3, OV 4; 1.4 linear feet)
  This series includes full issues of magazines illustrated by William Gropper including New Masses, Liberator and Der Hammer. There are also clippings from newspapers and magazines about William Gropper or featuring his illustrations. Gropper's illustrations appear in Hound Dog Moses and the Promised Land by Walter D. Edmonds and "In Gold We Trust (J.P. Morgan, Al. Capone and CO.)" by Larry Harr. There is one folder of Gropper's collection of first issue United Nations' postage stamps, one of which was illustrated by Gropper. Also included are auction catalogs, stationary, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Gropper's artwork, blank greeting cards, press releases and bulletins, and order forms.
  This series is arranged by type of materials. Clippings from magazines illustrated by Gropper have been filed before folders containing full issues of New Masses magazines that feature Gropper's illustrations. All dated material is arranged chronologically with undated material following.
  - Auction Catalogs, 1982-1983, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
  - Stationary and Enclosures, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Clippings, 1922-1964, undated, (See also Box 4; 7 folders) (Box 1, Folder 43-49)
  - Clippings, 1960-1983, undated, (See also Box 4; 6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Exibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1935-1983, undated, (See also Box 4; 13 folders) (Box 2, Folder 7-19)
  - Blank Greeting Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous, Art Related, 1974-1975, undated, (partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous, Not Art Related, undated, (not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Order Forms, 1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Collection of United Nations Postage Stamps, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Press Releases and Bulletins, 1935, 1945, 1971-1972, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Illustrations by Gropper, 1919-1943, (See also Box 4; 15 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-40)
  - Illustrations by Gropper, 1945-1960, 1967-1974, undated, (10 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-10)
  - New Masses, 1926-1928, 1934, 1936, (See also Box 4; 5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 11-15)
  - Oversized Clippings, (See Box 1, F45, F47 and Box 2, F1, F6) (Box 4 (sol))
  - Oversized Exhibition Announcements, (See Box 2, F14) (Box 4 (sol))
  - Oversized Illustrated by Gropper, (See Box 2, F26 and Box 3, F10) (Box 4 (sol))
  - Oversized New Masses, (See Box 3, F11) (Box 4 (sol))
- Photographs, after 1937-circa 1980s, Series 7:; (Box 3; 0.8 linear feet)
  This series includes photographs of William Gropper, his family, colleagues and friends. Additionally, there are photographs of works of art, slides from family vacations, negatives and duplicates.
  - William Gropper, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
  - William Gropper with Family, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Gropper Family, 1938, 1961-1970, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
  - Gropper Family Vacations, 1963, 1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Slides, Gropper Family, 1975, (not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Social Functions, 1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Colleagues and Friends, 1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Works of Art, Automobile Industry, Detroit, Michigan, after 1940, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
  - Works of Art, Construction of the Dam, Department of the Interior, Washington, D.C., after 1937, (not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Works of Art, Suburban Post in Winter, Freeport, New York, after 1938, (partially scanned) (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Works of Art, Murals, undated, (partially scanned) (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Works of Art, Sculpture and Ceramics, 1980s(?), undated, (not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Works of Art, Stained Glass, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Works of Art, 1968, undated, (18 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 33-50)
  - Works of Art, Miscellaneous, undated, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 51-52)
  - Duplicate Photographs, undated, (4 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 53-56)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Negatives, undated, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 58-59)
Index to Selected Correspondents
The following is an index to selected correspondents in Series 5: Correspondence. Although this index is not comprehensive, an effort has been made to highlight the major artists, museums and galleries with which William and Sophie Gropper corresponded.
Angelo, Emidio (artist): 1971; 1972
Ballot, Adele (Vanity Fair magazine): 1935
Barr, Alfred H. Jr. (The Museum of Modern Art): 1936
Bliven, Bruce (The New Republic): 1936
Broadley, Hugh (Phoenix Art Museum): 1968
Bromfield, Innes (Vanity Fair magazine): 1935
Butler, Joseph G. (Butler Institute of American Art): 1969
Cody, Bruce (Wisconsin State University): 1970
Conacher, Don (Galerie de Tours; Conacher Galleries): 1964; 1966; 1968
Constable, W. G. (Museum of Fine Arts, Boston): 1941
Crowninshield, Frank (Vanity Fair magazine): 1935; 1936
Dewitt, John (Department of the Interior): 1971
Doty, Robert M. (Whitney Museum of American Art): 1969
Dows, Olin (United States Treasury Department): 1936
Dreiser, Theodore (artist): 1934
Ealand, Maria (Federal Works Agency- Public Buildings Administration): 1939; 1940
Eastman, Crystal (The Liberator): 1919
Foley, Martha (Story magazine): 1936
Force, Juliana (The Whitney Museum of American Art): 1939
Garson, Inez (Cornell University): 1964
Gibbs, Wolcott (The New Yorker): 1936
Gillette, Guy M. (United States Senator, Iowa): 1949
Gorney, Jay (ACA Galleries): 1975
Gould, Beatrice Blackman (Ladies' Home Journal): 1937
Gropper, Lance (grandson): 1969
Gross, Hilda (ACA Galleries): 1979
Harkavy, Susan (ACA Galleries): 1981
Hayes, Bartlett H. Jr. (Addison Gallery): 1964
Heintzelman, Arthur W. (Boston Public Library): 1953
Henri, Robert (artist): 1921
Hinchman, R. L. (Lord and Thomas Advertising): 1935
Hirsch, Joseph (National Academy of Design): 1972; 1973
Horowitz, Ben (Heritage Gallery): 1968-1976; 1982; undated
Hyman, Linda (ACA Galleries): 1981
Kainen, Jacob (National Collection of Fine Arts): 1969
Korn, Gail (Whitney Museum of American Art): 1967
Lamson, James Q. (Ohio University): 1973
Lerner, Abram (Hirshhorn Museum, New York): 1972
Lewis, John L. (United Mine Workers of America): 1936
Lozowick, Louis (artist): 1970-1973; undated
Malawer, Lisa (ACA Galleries): 1982
Mannes, Marya (Vogue magazine): 1936
Meador, Philip L. (Galerie de Tours): 1964
McCabe, Cynthia (Hirshhorn Museum, New York): 1972
McGuire, Harry (Ringmaster magazine): 1936
McLouth, Mildred (Berkeley Art Museum): 1931
Minnigerode, C. Powell (Corcoran Gallery of Art): 1943
Newman, Dorothy (M. H. DeYoung Memorial Museum)
O'Conner, Francis V. (NCFA, Smithsonian Institution): 1970
Owen, William B. (United States Treasury Department): 1937
Palmer, William C. (Mural Painters Society): 1936
Parsons, Frank Alvah (New York School of Fine and Applied Art): 1916
Rhodes, Reilly P. (Canton Art Institute): 1971; 1972
Rogerson, Ann S. (Montclair Art Museum): 1969
Rowan, Edward B. (United States Treasury Department): 1935; 1937; 1939; 1941
Saint-Gaudens, Homer (Carnegie Institute): 1947
Schmeckebler, Laurence (Syracuse University): 1964
Schoener, Allon (Jewish Museum, New York): 1966
Sharkey, Alice (United States Treasury Department): 1936
Singer, Clyde (Butler Institute of American Art): 1973
Soby, James Thrall (The Museum of Modern Art): 1964
SoRelle, Jane (ACA Gallery, Rome): 1964
Soyer, Raphael (artist): 1947; 1970
Taylor, Francis Henry (The Museum of Modern Art): 1942
Tolley, William P. (Syracuse University): 1968
United States Treasury Department: 1935
Vanity Fair magazine: 1935
Valeska, S. (Valeska Art Studios): 1966
Watson, Forbes (United States Treasury Department): 1936; 1942
Winser, Beatrice (Newark Museum): 1935
Yasko, Karel (Public Buildings Service): 1969; 1971; 1977; undated
Young, Art (artist): 1934